Guide to the James Hazen Hyde Papers 1874-1940, 1953 MS 319
New-York Historical Society
James Hazen Hyde papers
1874-1940, 1953
New-York Historical Society
Hyde, James H. (James Hazen), 1876-1959
MS 319
31.67 Linear feet in 34 boxes, 6 oversize volumes, and 2 oversize folders
Collection consists of correspondence, diaries, scrapbooks, photographs, and other papers of James Hazen Hyde (1876-1959). The papers are especially strong in two areas: documentation of Hyde's efforts at expanding knowledge of French culture in America from circa 1894-1905 through the Cercle Français de l'Université Harvard and the Fédération de l'Alliance Francaise, and documentation of his activities as an expatriate living in France from 1906 to 1941. His correspondence includes a large collection of letters to and from his mother, Annie F. Hyde, from 1891-1921; documentation of Red Cross activities in France during World War I; and Hyde's ongoing initiatives to expand Franco-American cultural exchange. His correspondence and diaries (which date from 1922-1940) include extensive references to Hyde's social life, anecdotes and comments about prominent persons, especially diplomats, government officials, military officers, academics, journalists, industrialists, and those from cultural circles from France, the United States, and Britain. Most of the collection is in French.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in eight series:
Series I. General Correspondence (1878, 1892-1939, 1953)
Series II. Correspondence with Annie Fitch Hyde (circa 1891-1922)
Series III: Correspondence Concerning Federation de l'Alliance Francaise (1898-1935)
Series IV. Diaries (1922-1940)
Series V. Cercle Francais and Other, Related Scrapbooks (1894-1905)
Series VI. Legion of Honor Letter Books (1921, 1923, 1928)
Series VII. Henry Baldwin Hyde Memorial Books (1874, 1894, 1899-1900)
Series VIII. Photographs and Certificates (circa 1880s-1953)
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
James Hazen Hyde made various donations in a piecemeal fashion to N-YHS over the course of the 1940s and 1950s. This collection includes most of the personal papers he donated. The various acquisition dates for the materials in Series III-VII are noted at the series level. All those materials were donated with Hyde's stipulation that they would not be made available until after his death, which occurred in 1959.
It is not clear when the correspondence in Series I and II was donated. At points in the 1940s and 1950s, Hyde informed N-YHS's director at the time that he was going through the correspondence to identify what he would donate (he was discarding "uninteresting and personal letters"), again with the stipulation that it would not be available until after his death. A list of notable correspondents is in the archive from 1959 so the correspondence was donated no later than then.
Related Materials
Over the course of the 1940s-1950s, Hyde made many donations to New-York Historical of manuscripts, photographs, prints, objects, and other material. These arrived in a piecemeal fashion and were separated to various departments and collections in the library and museum. Following are some of the Hyde donations related to this collection:
The following manuscripts were donated by Hyde and cataloged under separate call numbers:
* A small collection of six letters titled "James Hazen Hyde collection" (call AHMC - Hyde, James Hazen)
* George Henry Nettleton letter to James Hazen Hyde, 1947 March 24 (call AHMC - Nettleton, George Henry)
* Woodrow Wilson letter to James H. Hyde, 1903 March 16 (call AHMC - Wilson, Woodrow – Hyde)
* An exchange between Hyde and Charles Francis Adams in the Charles Francis Adams papers (call AHMC - Adams, Charles Francis (1835-1915))
N-YHS's institutional archive holds correspondence related to Hyde's various donations. See the New-York Historical Society General Correspondence record group (NYHS-RG 2) and search for Hyde.
The Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections holds the James H. Hyde collection of allegorical prints of the four continents (PR-27).
A search on James Hazen Hyde in N-YHS's catalog, Bobcat, will yield other print matter related to Hyde, including works authored by Hyde.
Some of the correspondence files in this collection refer to Hyde's efforts to create a "New Theatre" in New York. These happen to be outliers from a larger set of correspondence originally in Hyde's files. Among the many donations Hyde offered to N-YHS in the 1950s was his "dossier" concerning Winthrop Ames and the development of the New Theatre, which opened in 1909. N-YHS's director at the time suggested to Hyde that those papers be donated to the New York Public Library, which held extensive related material. These can be found at NYPL under the title James Hazen Hyde papers (call MssCol 1471).
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of James Hazen Hyde's correspondence, diaries, scrapbooks, photographs, and other papers dating primarily from the 1890s, when he was an undergraduate student at Harvard, through 1940, shortly before he returned to the United States from France. Hyde's involvement with the Cercle Français de l'Université Harvard and the Fédération de l'Alliance Francaise in the 1890s-circa 1904 are well-documented in correspondence and scrapbooks. Hyde's diaries begin in 1922 and end in 1940, that is, for the latter half of his time residing in France. They include details of his social engagements, anecdotes and comments about prominent persons, descriptions of his travel, and visits to cultural events and institutions, and include clippings, theatre and opera programs, and other print matter related to his activities and interests.
Hyde's correspondence files extend principally from the 1890s to the 1930s, and especially pertain to his interest in Franco-American relations, e.g. American Field Service Fellowships, arranging American lecture tours by French professors and vice versa, and his work in the American Red Cross in France during World War I. Hyde's correspondents include diplomats, government officials, military officers, academics, journalists, industrialists, and those from cultural circles, though the extent and substance of each is uneven. The container list of the finding aid includes an inventory of the correspondents. Especially rich is a large collection of correspondence between Hyde and his mother, Annie Fitch Hyde, from 1891 to 1921. Much of the correspondence files include both incoming and Hyde's outgoing letters. Although the correspondence with his mother and others touch at times on financial and business matters, there seems to be relatively little on Hyde's activities as an Equitable Assurance Company officer or in his other commercial enterprises prior to departing the U.S. in 1905.
One set of bound volumes in the collection hold congratulatory letters to Hyde on his promotions within the French Legion of Honor in the 1920s. Another set are memorial books with condolence letters and other documents related to the death of Hyde's father, Henry Baldwin Hyde in 1899. There are a few family photographs and diplomas/certificates.
An extensive amount of the collection, likely well more than half, is in French. Some, especially print matter in the diaries, is in German.
Biographical / Historical
James Hazen Hyde (1876-1959) was born in New York City, the son of Henry Baldwin Hyde (1834-1899), who had founded the Equitable Life Assurance Company of the United States in 1859, and Annie (Fitch) Hyde (1845-1922). Hyde attended Cutler School in New York and entered Harvard College in 1894. At some point in his youth, Hyde picked up the nickname "Caleb" and correspondence from family and some friends used that name when addressing him.
A lifelong Francophile, Hyde joined the Cercle Francais de l'Universite Harvard, a society of students interested in French culture and literature and proficient in the language. While president of the club in 1897, Hyde received from his father $30,000 to form a trust to fund annual French lectures at Harvard under the auspices of the Cercle Francais. The first of these was delivered in March 1898 by René Doumic. Hyde's initiative led to him being named a member (Chevalier) of the French Legion of Honor in 1900. He would be promoted to the highest ranks in the Legion in the 1920s. In 1904, Hyde supported a counterpart program in France, whereby American academics from Harvard would lecture at the Sorbonne and France's provincial universities; Barrett Wendell was the first of these lecturers. (See the Harvard Register of 1905-06, page 88 (on-line) and, especially, Hyde's description to George Nettleton in this collection of the Cercle and later lectures and Hyde's involvement with them.)
After graduating from Harvard in 1898 with degrees in German and French, Hyde joined his father at the Equitable in the high-ranking position of Second Vice-President. At the time, Hyde's father, Henry, was president and controlling shareholder of the company he had founded, having built it into a firm with perhaps 600,000 policyholders and $400 million of assets. Henry died the following year, in 1899, at age 65, bequeathing to his son the controlling shares. Equitable's First Vice-President James W. Alexander ascended to the presidency and Hyde advanced to First Vice-President.
Over the next few years, Hyde expanded his financial interests, taking on directorships of various banking and other firms. His wealth also grew and his passion for French culture continued, both of which he flaunted. And his position as First Vice-President at Equitable put him in line to become company president. These factors culminated in Hyde's downfall as a businessman in 1905. In January of that year he hosted an ostentatious Versailles-themed costume ball for New York's wealthy elite. The extreme extravagance of the event led to not only general criticism in the press, but investigations into whether Hyde had misappropriated company funds for the purpose. Those at the Equitable looking to oust him from his position of power used the opportunity to deride him as reckless and unfit for the management of a financial firm. By the end of the year Hyde had resigned his position at the Equitable and his many directorships and sold his controlling interest in Equitable to Thomas Fortune Ryan. In December 1905, he sailed to France, where he would live until 1941, returning to America only when forced in the face of Nazi Germany's defeat of France.
During his years in France, Hyde leveraged his wealth to rebuild his reputation, remaking himself as a philanthropist, patron of the arts, and cultural ambassador. As a foundation, he expanded on the French-American cultural exchanges he had begun during his college years. In 1911, when Harvard formalized its own exchange of professors with the Sorbonne, Hyde redirected trust funds to support a continuing series of Harvard lecturers visiting the provinces. He maintained relationships with American diplomats, journalists, military officials, and others, acting as an unofficial guide to French culture and point of introduction to important French contacts. He traveled widely in Europe, and also to the Middle and Far East, enabling him to be a source of information for Americans new to the European scene. He delivered public remarks at times and wrote newspaper articles. During World War I, he gave over his home at 18 rue Adolphe Yvon in Paris to the Red Cross to use as a hospital and he worked as aide to Colonel Harvey D. Gibson, Commissioner for France of the American Red Cross.
After WWI, when the American Field Service created its Fellowships for French Universities, Hyde was on the Advisory Board. In the 1920s, Hyde was on the Executive Committee of the Continental Division of the American University in Europe, among other positions involving cultural exchange. As a philanthropist, among the many projects he supported were Albert Lythgoe's Egyptian archaeological expeditions and the acquisition and restoration of Madame Pompadour's residence at Versailles. He collected art, including a large number of allegorical prints now in the collections of New-York Historical Society. In recognition of his cultural and philanthropic services, Hyde was awarded the Grand Cross of the Legion of Honor in 1928 and was elected to the French Academy of Political and Moral Sciences in 1938, among other honors.
In 1913 in Paris, Hyde married for the first time and his wedding was emblematic of his French-American interconnections. His bride was Countess Louis de Gontaut-Biron, whose first husband, a member of the old French aristocracy, had died in 1907. She was American, her maiden name being Marthe Leishman, the daughter of a former United States ambassador to Germany. Hyde's best man was Myron T. Herrick, the American ambassador to France. The Hydes had one son, Henry Baldwin Hyde (1915-1997), and they divorced in 1918; the New York Times reported that the cause was Marthe's sympathies toward the Germans during World War I. Nonetheless, as Hyde's diaries show, Marthe and Hyde stayed in touch over the years, notably in connection with their son; Marthe sent congratulations to Hyde on the occasion of his promotion to Grand Officer of the Legion of Honor in 1923 (see Series V, Volume 3).
Hyde remarried in 1930, to Countess Ella Matuschka, who was also an American (from Detroit) and who was previously married to a German officer. Hyde left her in 1931 and was sued for divorce in 1932. That same year, Hyde married a third time to Madame Thome (nee Stephanie Dervaux?), whose husband, Andre Thome, had been killed at Verdun.
On his return to the United States in 1941, Hyde lived at the Savoy-Plaza Hotel in New York and summered in Saratoga Springs. Over time in the 1940s and 1950s, he donated his papers and some of his artwork to the New-York Historical Society. He died of pneumonia in 1959 at the Gideon Putnam Hotel in Saratoga Springs.
Clippings (information artifacts).; Diaries.; Letters (correspondence).; Programs (documents).; Scrapbooks.; Antisemitism; Aliens -- France; Cultural relations; Educational exchange; Geopolitics -- Europe; Insurance companies -- New York (State); Manners and customs; Philanthropists; World War, 1914-1918; France -- Politics and government -- 20th century; Allen, Henry T. (Henry Tureman), 1859-1930; Andrew, A. Piatt (Abram Piatt), 1873-1936; Azan, Paul, 1874-1951; Barrès, Maurice, 1862-1923; Barthou, Louis, 1862-1934; Bergson, Henri, 1859-1941; Berthelot, Philippe, 1866-1934; Breasted, James Henry, 1865-1935; Cambon, Jules, 1845-1935; Carrel, Alexis, 1873-1944; Clemenceau, Georges, 1841-1929; Clifton, Chalmers, 1889-1966; Coolidge, Archibald Cary, 1866-1928; Cuyler, Thomas Dewitt, 1854-1922; Depew, Chauncey M. (Chauncey Mitchell), 1834-1928; Doumer, Paul, 1857-1932; Doumic, René, 1860-1937; Ferrero, Guglielmo, 1871-1942; Finley, John H. (John Huston), 1863-1940; Foch, Ferdinand, 1851-1929; Ford, J. D. M. (Jeremiah Denis Matthias), 1873-1958; Funck-Brentano, Frantz, 1862-1947; Frick, Henry Clay, 1849-1919; Gardner, Isabella Stewart, 1840-1924; Garner, James Wilford, 1871-1938; Gouraud, Henri, 1867-1946; Gregory, Eliot, 1854-1915; Herrick, Myron T. (Myron Timothy), 1854-1929; Hyde, Annie Fitch, 1845-1922; Kahn, Otto H., 1867-1934; Kerney, James, 1873-1934; Lavisse, Ernest, 1842-1922; Le Braz, Anatole, 1859-1926; Lebrun, Albert, 1871-1950; Lecomte, Georges, 1867-1958; Morris, Gouverneur, 1876-1953; Ochs, Adolph S. (Adolph Simon), 1858-1935; Peabody, Endicott, 1857-1944; Perry, Bliss, 1860-1954; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948; Poincaré, Lucien, 1862-1920; Poincaré, Raymond, 1860-1934; Prévost, Marcel, 1862-1941; Recouly, Raymond, 1876-1950; Rodin, Auguste, 1840-1917; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Roy, Edouard; Régnier, Henri de, 1864-1936; Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1874-1958; Strong, Eugénie, 1860-1943; Sumichrast, Frederick C. de (Frederick Caesar de), 1845-1933; Tardieu, André, 1876-1945; Untermyer, Samuel, 1858-1940; Ward, John Quincy Adams, 1830-1910; Weill, Félix, 1871-; Westinghouse, George, 1846-1914; American Field Service; American Field Service Fellowships for French Universities, Inc.; American Red Cross in France; Cercle français (Harvard University); Equitable Life Assurance Society of the United States; Federation of French Alliances in the United States and Canada; Harvard University; Metropolitan Opera (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I. General Correspondence, 1878, 1892-1939, 1953; 5.1 Linear feet in 13 boxes and one oversize folder
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes Hyde's incoming and outgoing correspondence dating primarily from his years living in France. Correspondents include both French and American politicians, diplomats, military officers, journalists, editors, writers, scholars, and others. Most of the correspondence is in French. Subject matter pertains to his interest in Franco-American relations, American Field Service Fellowships, American lecture tours by French professors and vice versa, his work for the American Red Cross in France during World War I, his social life, philanthropy, support for the arts and cultural endeavors, anecdotes and comments about prominent persons. Some correspondence dates from the 1890s and early years of the twentieth century, before Hyde left the United States for France. Letters from that early period generally concern business matters. The series also includes copies of some remarks given by Hyde in public presentations after World War I.
  Several of the files include an index card with typed explanatory notes about the correspondent or subject. It seems likely that these were prepared by Hyde as he prepared the files for donation to N-YHS. This view is based on an exchange Hyde had with N-YHS director R.W.G. Vail in 1950 in which Hyde asked whether he should annotate the original documents with comments, to which Vail suggested the addition of typed memos to the file instead. (See N-YHS's institutional archive, General Correspondence record group (NYHS-RG 2).
  The container list includes a detailed list of most of the correspondents in the series. All correspondents filed separately are listed and most correspondents in the "miscellaneous" correspondents are identified. Some correspondents are not listed because their name was illegible or because they were included in folders under another correspondent's name.
  An attempt was made to note any potentially substantive subject matter at the folder level. However, a significant constraint on this was the fact that most of the letters are in French and the processing archivists could not read French.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  Within folders for each correspondent, the original order appears to have been reverse chronological (i.e., latest documents at front of folder, moving backward in time to the earliest at back of folder). Generally, the documents remain in this order. However, during processing some select folders were re-arranged to chronological order to facilitate use.
  Many folders include some undated documents. The presence of such documents was noted explicitly in the container list only if there were a substantial number of them and if these undated might not be fairly represented by the dated documents.
  - Adams, Charles F, 1896-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Business associate and friend from Harvard. Discussion of financial matters. Hyde describes interest in Franco-American relations and living in France. Also includes letters from Charles F. Adams 2nd.
  - Allen, Henry T. (General), 1919-1923 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    American general from World War I. Letters primarily concern arrangements to meet at various times and places. Various mentions of post-war issues, such as the timing of withdrawal of American forces.
  - Allenby, Edmund, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Donated to the British National Cadet Association, asked to do so anonymously. Hyde also refers to his coming marriage to Countess Matuschka.
  - American Field Service Fellowships for French Universities, 1920-1924 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Hyde was on the advisory board and the Paris Committee of this organization. Concerns the American Field Service Scholarship Fund, various other donations (including the proceeds of Georges Clemenceau's lecture tour in America), and organizational matters. Includes correspondence from one of the organization's vice-presidents, A. Piatt Andrew, some meeting minutes, publicity materials.
  - American Red Cross - Boulogne s/ Mer, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Stated commmunication was received and that further letters would not be necessary. Original communication not present.
  - American Red Cross - Miscellaneous, 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Secured a laboratory for Stationary Hospital 12, and other arrangements, including an African-American banjo player for Thanksgiving and Christmas. Several communications in French.
  - American Red Cross - Brest, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Involved with US military plans to reorganize the Red Cross system throughout France.
  - American Red Cross (Dans Militaires), 1915, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Primarily letters of thanks to Hyde for contributions toward Christmas dinners.
  - American Red Cross (Installation des Directeurs de Zones), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Red Cross - Lyon, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Unsatisfactory care due to being short-staffed. Installation of new officers for the region.
  - American Red Cross - Marseille, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Red Cross-Nantes, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - American Red Cross (Papiers Divers), 1918 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Contains information on management, key contacts, and logistics for the American Red Cross.
  - American Red Cross - Paris, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - American Relief Clearing House, 1916-1917 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Includes, among other matters, Hyde's reports on his trips to hospitals in the Verdun and Somme regions.
  - Andrew, A. Piatt, 1907-1926 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Includes, among others, letters on the stationery of the Field Service of the American Ambulance.
  - Azan, Paul (Colonel), 1917-1933 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - B. Miscellaneous, 1901-1931 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Correspondents include, among others, Leon Bakst, French diplomat Barere, Henry Berenger, Leon Blum, Andre Blum, General Belin, Carl Boyd, Rene Boylesve, Captain Boutal, Comte Bonin-Longare, Andre Bellessort, Emile Borel, Philippe Bunau-Varilla, Henri Bremond, H. Berthon, V. Berard, Jean Babelon.
  - Bacon, Robert, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Baldensperger, Fernand, 1913-1935 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bangs, John Kendrick, 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 20A)
    Two handwritten letters from Hyde: thanking Bangs for his note declining to attend Hyde's party because of a trip to Cuba (1904) and acknowledging Bangs's recent note and his friendly interest and courtesy (1905). (Source: These two letters were donated to N-YHS in May 2019 by Christine Durling, and added to the Hyde papers at that time.)
  - Barres, Maurice (de l'Academie Francaise), 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Barthou, Louis, 1910-1924 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Also includes correspondence with Pierre Loti.
  - Bayet, A, 1904-1914 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bedier, Joseph, 1911-1935 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bennett, James Gordon & Maud, 1912-1917 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bergson, Henri, 1909-1934 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Berthelot, Philippe & Helene (2 folders), 1912-1930 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Bliss, Robert Woods & Mildred, 1914-1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bocher, Ferdinand, 1896-1902 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bourgeois, Emile, 1920-1929 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Boutroux, Emile & Aline (de l'Academie Francaise), 1907-1921 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Breasted, James Henry, 1924-1935 (Box 2, Folder 10)